Reuven Frank Papers MS137
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Reuven Frank Papers
1940 -- 2008
Digital Collections and Archives, Tufts University
Frank, Reuven
MS137
12 Linear Feet 10 record cartons
3 Digital Object(s)
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: Research and reference files; Awards and photographs; and AV materials.
Custodial History
The material was donated to the archives in the summer of 2007.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists mostly of secondary source research material (largely photocopies of articles) assembled by Reuven Frank for his book, Out of Thin Air: The Brief Wonderful Life of Network News from the late twentieth century. Material not related to his book includes awards for achievements in journalism, numerous photographs, and AV materials of mostly NBC documentaries and special reports. Of note is a 1963-1964 Emmy Award for Outstanding Achievement in News Reporting.
Biographical / Historical
Born in 1920 in Montreal, Quebec, Canada, Reuven Frank helped transform the world of television journalism when radio still dominated the airwaves. A graduate of Columbia University's prestigious Graduate School of Journalism, Frank also served in the U.S. Army for four years during World War II, two of them in Europe. Upon his return, Frank married Bernice Kaplow on June 9, 1946. They later had two sons, Peter and James, and eventually a grandson and granddaughter.
Frank joined NBC in 1950 as a writer after spending three years at Newark Evening News (Newark, N.J.) where he made his mark as an editor, rewrite man, and a reporter. As an executive at NBC News for much of the latter half of the twentieth century, Frank helped to solidify the importance of the medium with his emphasis on the visual power of television. As a standard, Frank believed in "the transmission of the experience, rather than the transmission of information" as a way of developing many of his newscasts.
As producer of such news shows as The Huntley-Brinkley Report, which later became NBC Nightly News, Frank also was the first to pair two anchors together in a broadcast. The show began on October 29, 1956, and ended in 1970. He also oversaw the transition of the nightly news from a standard 15-minute format to a half-hour format. Described as a wise and quiet man but with a dry wit, Mr. Frank noted one of his contributions to the field in his memoir, Out of Thin Air: The Brief Wonderful Life of Network News. As they struggled to find an ending for Huntley-Brinkley each night, he typed out the words, "Good night, Chet," and "Good night, David" - also evoking Edward R. Murrow's famous 'Good Night and Good Luck' line. The ending stuck and became one of the most recognizable phrases during that era. Putting different journalists in different cities talking to each other on television, as this show did with Huntley in New York and Brinkley in Washington, also helped reinforce standards for television news broadcasts.
As a news medium, television was ripe for experimentation and Frank did just that with news segments such as Background, Chet Huntley Reporting, and Frank McGee Reports. This documentary-style of news making was still quite revolutionary for the 1950s and allowed Frank to hone his skills in writing commentary, editing, and creative visuals. He won an Emmy Award for his documentary, The Tunnel, which told the story of a group of West Berlin students who helped 59 men, women, and children escape through a tunnel underneath the newly constructed Berlin Wall in 1962. It was the only documentary to win an Emmy Award for Program of the Year during the award ceremony.
Frank won numerous awards throughout his career, including The Broadcast Man of the Year Award from the Missouri Broadcasters Association, and the Sigma Delta Chi Award for "distinguished service in the field of television writing" for his script of The Road to Spandau. He was named a Poynter Fellow by Yale University in 1970, and was the first individual from the field of television to receive that honor. His later achievements included two Peabody Awards for his efforts as executive producer of the critically acclaimed nightly news program, Weekend. The Peabody committee recognized the show as "a new and refreshing approach to television programming, providing the viewer with a quality experience." He also wrote articles for magazines and newspapers.
Reuven Frank forged new ground with the method of coverage used during political conventions. His technique consisted of anchoring four floor reporters among the politicians, and then to record their reports using live cameras. The communication center controlled the "news gathering, reporting, and distribution" of the broadcasts. Once the communication center decided on a report, the technical team would execute it. This system became standard.
Frank was seminal in developing some of the most influential news programs on television, and was appointed president of NBC News in the turbulent year of 1968. During such events as the Tet offensive in Vietnam and the assassinations of Rev. Martin Luther King, Jr. and Robert F. Kennedy, Frank was a formidable force in shaping the ways news broadcasts were executed. After being producer, Vice President, Executive Vice President and finally President of NBC News from 1968 until 1973, he again worked on special programs and documentaries for the next nine years. In 1982 he again accepted the post of President and helped to select Tom Brokaw as the solo anchor of NBC Nightly News in 1983. After Robert E. Mulholland took over for Frank in 1984 as President of NBC he said, "Reuven wrote the book on how television covers the political process in America, has trained more top broadcast journalists than anyone alive, and simply embodies the very best professional traditions of NBC News."
Frank passed away on February 5, 2006, in Englewood, N.J., of complications from pneumonia.
Conditions Governing Access
This collection contains some restricted material. Restrictions related to specific material are listed in the detailed contents list. This collection may require review before it is available for use. Please contact DCA for further details.
Television broadcasting of news -- United States -- History.; Media and broadcast history
- Research and reference files, 1940 -- 2006; MS137.001; 4.8 Linear Feet
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains research and reference materials primarily for Mr. Frank's book, Out of Thin Air: The Brief Wonderful Life of Network News.
  Arrangement
  This series is arranged numerically.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Open for research.
  - Weekend, 1974 -- 1979; MS137.001.001.00001 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence with Fred Silverman.
    Frank, Reuven
  - RLA Bradshaw, 1978 -- 1987; MS137.001.001.00002 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence.
  - Horace W. Hostile, 1948 -- 1968; MS137.001.001.00003 (Box 1)
  - Herring, 1968 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00004 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence with Lloyd Dobyns.
  - Brinkley, 1968 -- 1982; MS137.001.001.00005 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence with David Brinkley.
  - Gunga Dan, 1987 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00006 (Box 1)
  - Misc. Sheer History, 1951 -- 1989; MS137.001.001.00007 (Box 1)
  - 1948 Conventions Pix and c, 1948 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00008 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence and photographs.
  - Like a Colossus, 1962 -- 1989; MS137.001.001.00009 (Box 1)
  - Deadlier Than, 1988 -- 1989; MS137.001.001.00010 (Box 1)
  - The Other Place, 1988; MS137.001.001.00011 (Box 1)
  - Brokaw, 1987 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00012 (Box 1)
  - Obits for Network News, 1986 -- 1993; MS137.001.001.00013 (Box 1)
  - Regulation Fairness AIM, 1972 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00014 (Box 1)
  - It's Local But Is It News?, 1987 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00015 (Box 1)
  - News Versus Talk, 1987 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00016 (Box 1)
    Includes correspondence with Jim Lehrer.
  - New Toys Make New News, 1987 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00017 (Box 1)
  - The New News, 1987 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00018 (Box 1)
  - Contracts, 1980 -- 1982; MS137.001.001.00019 (Box 1)
  - 1953 Coronation Inc. Logs-NBC, 1952 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00020 (Box 1)
  - Larger Forms General (Part II), 1950 -- 1975; MS137.001.001.00021 (Box 1)
    Includes photograph.
  - The Reporter Myth, 1987 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00022 (Box 1)
  - Usable Quotes, 1988 -- 1996; MS137.001.001.00023 (Box 1)
  - GE Bringing Good Things to the Bottom Line, 1986; MS137.001.001.00024 (Box 1)
  - Tunnel, 1962 -- 1988; MS137.001.001.00025 (Box 1)
  - More Tunnel, 1962 -- 1989; MS137.001.001.00026 (Box 1)
  - Pers. Misc., 1967 -- 1986; MS137.001.002.00001 (Box 2)
    Includes correspondence with Grant Tinker.
  - Writings, Misc, 1974 -- 1977; MS137.001.002.00002 (Box 2)
  - Spchs: SDX, Mo, Omaha, 1970 -- 1981; MS137.001.002.00003 (Box 2)
  - Writings, 1963 -- 1980; MS137.001.002.00004 (Box 2)
  - Writings and Tokyo, RF: Speech: Tokyo-5/71 Seminar of Documentarians, 1971 -- 1977; MS137.001.002.00005 (Box 2)
  - TV Guide Chica 68, Spandau/Harpers, 1943 -- 1968; MS137.001.002.00006 (Box 2)
  - Personal, 1965 -- 1987; MS137.001.002.00007 (Box 2)
  - Speeches: Milwaukee (Law) J-School (Inst AN) RTNDA Keynote, 1951 -- 1987; MS137.001.002.00008 (Box 2)
  - Weaver-Today, 1951 -- 1987; MS137.001.002.00009 (Box 2)
  - Elections: Frankel Memos, 1982; MS137.001.002.00010 (Box 2)
  - Pers: Articles, 48 and Coro, 1980 -- 1981; MS137.001.002.00011 (Box 2)
  - Headshots, Project: Censored, Correspondence, 1988 -- 1994; MS137.001.002.00012 (Box 2)
  - Misc. pers. clippings, DEP, 1966 -- 1989; MS137.001.002.00013 (Box 2)
  - History and pers-RF intro, 1971 -- 1986; MS137.001.002.00014 (Box 2)
  - 1960 Conventions NBC Logs Pre Dem and Rep, MS137.001.002.00015 (Box 2)
  - 1964 Conventions NBC Logs Clips-Hewitt Theft Elec. Nite, MS137.001.002.00016 (Box 2)
  - 1968 Dem Conv NBC Logs Platform and Convention, MS137.001.003.00001 (Box 3)
  - '68 Supp. Election Nite Articles, 1968 -- 1969; MS137.001.003.00002 (Box 3)
  - Conv 1948 and Misc Temp (Bob Doyle) (1956), 1948 -- 1988; MS137.001.003.00003 (Box 3)
  - 1948 Conv NBC Logs All 3 Parties, 1948 -- 1988; MS137.001.003.00004 (Box 3)
    Includes correspondence. Oversized; on the bottom of the box.
  - 1948 Conv NBC Logs All 3 Parties, MS137.001.003.00005 (Box 3)
  - 1948 Conv NBC Logs All 3 Parties, MS137.001.003.00006 (Box 3)
  - 1948 Conv NBC Logs All 3 Parties, MS137.001.003.00007 (Box 3)
  - 1948 Conv Misc, 1947 -- 1988; MS137.001.003.00008 (Box 3)
  - Election Nite NBC Logs '52 '60 '68, 1952; MS137.001.003.00009 (Box 3)
  - NBC Logs 1952 Conventions (Both), MS137.001.003.00010 (Box 3)
  - 1956 Both Conventions NBC Logs, MS137.001.003.00011 (Box 3)
  - 1972 Dem. Conv. NBC Logs, MS137.001.003.00012 (Box 3)
  - 1988-1989 Published, MS137.001.003.00013 (Box 3)
  - RFK Ass'n June '68 NBC Logs, 1968; MS137.001.003.00014 (Box 3)
  - J.F.K. Assassination Weekend-NBC Logs, 1963; MS137.001.003.00015 (Box 3)
  - [NBC article, box list, and personal correspondence], 1987 -- 2000; MS137.001.003.00016 (Box 3)
  - Thorndike Press G.K. Hall, 2001; MS137.001.003.00017 (Box 3)
  - Zionist Handbook, 1968 -- 1970; MS137.001.003.00018 (Box 3)
  - [Political conventions manuscript], 1980; MS137.001.003.00019 (Box 3)
    Date is an educated guess.
  - Address Lists, 1963 -- 1974; MS137.001.003.00020 (Box 3)
  - [Personal correspondence and research notes], 1963 -- 1980; MS137.001.003.00021 (Box 3)
  - Magazines-Press Excess, 1982 -- 1995; MS137.001.003.00022 (Box 3)
  - [Political articles and magazines], 1976 -- 1988; MS137.001.003.00023 (Box 3)
  - [New York Times article], 1956; MS137.001.003.00024 (Box 3)
  - [Nieman Reports and Vital Speeches of the Day], 1970 -- 1971; MS137.001.003.00025 (Box 3)
  - [Address lists, notes, and correspondence], 1988 -- 1989; MS137.001.003.00026 (Box 3)
  - Foreward, MS137.001.003.00027 (Box 3)
  - 1948 Additional; MOT-Television-Misc, MS137.001.003.00028 (Box 3)
  - [Correspondence], 1996; MS137.001.003.00029 (Box 3)
  - Today: The First Fifteen Years, 1966; MS137.001.004.00001 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - Late book-2 B filed, 1962 -- 1986; MS137.001.004.00002 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - 68-70 Agrew Speech, Vietnam, Nixon Campaign, U.S. Networks; Late-TV Misc, 1968 -- 1989; MS137.001.004.00003 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Research articles and interviews], 2001 -- 2004; MS137.001.004.00004 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - For Archivist; [personal speeches and written works], 1963 -- 1971; MS137.001.004.00005 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - Threats to Press FR, 1997; MS137.001.004.00006 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Newspaper clippings and correspondence], 1940 -- 1990; MS137.001.004.00007 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
    Dates span the decades
  - [Correspondence, written works, and clippings], 1963 -- 1997; MS137.001.004.00008 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Journals and research articles], 1986 -- 2006; MS137.001.004.00009 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Remembrance program and correspondence], 1959 -- 2006; MS137.001.004.00010 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Clippings and research articles], MS137.001.004.00011 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Manuscripts], 1970; MS137.001.004.00012 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
    Dates span the decade
  - [Correspondence, journals, and clippings], 1950 -- 1999; MS137.001.004.00013 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Manuscripts, correspondence, journals, and clippings], 1940 -- 1960; MS137.001.004.00014 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - Scrapbook, 1940; MS137.001.004.00015 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - Out of Thin Air: The Brief Wonderful Life of Network News, 1991; MS137.001.004.00016 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
- Awards and photographs, 1950 -- 1991; MS137.002; 3.6 Linear Feet; 2 Digital Object(s)
  This series contains various awards and photographs, mainly documenting Mr. Frank's professional life and achievements. Dates for the awards range from 1955-1991. Dates for the photographs range approximately from the 1950's-1980's. Of note is a 1963-1964 Emmy Award for Outstanding Achievement in News Reporting.
  The awards are arranged chronologically, followed by two folders of photographs.
  - [Awards], 1955 -- 1988; MS137.002.004.00017 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - The National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences; Outstanding Achievements in the Field of Documentary Programs; "The Tunnel,", 1962; MS137.002.004.00018 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - The National Academy of Television Arts and Sciences; The Programs of the Year; "The Tunnel,", 1962; MS137.002.004.00019 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - Champion-Tuck Awards; For Outstanding Reporting that Improves the Public's Understanding of Business and Economic Issues, 1985; MS137.002.004.00020 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - American Women In Radio and Television Inc. Award, 1991; MS137.002.004.00021 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Photographs], 1950 -- 1970; MS137.002.004.00022 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - [Photographs], 1950 -- 1980; MS137.002.004.00023 (Box MS137 Shared 1)
  - 1963-1964 Awards; Outstanding Program Achievement In the Field of News Reports; Huntley-Brinkley Report-NBC, MS137.002.007.00001 (Box 7)
    Emmy Award.
  - Reuven Frank, seated portrait with arms crossed, 1960; MS137.002.008.00001; Unknown
    Portraits; Television broadcasting; Frank, Reuven
  - Reuven Frank standing in front of control panel, 1970 -- 1985; MS137.002.008.00002; Unknown
    Television broadcasting; Frank, Reuven
  - George Foster Peabody Braodcasting Award, 1976; MS137.002.009.00001 (Box 9)
    The award is presented to NBC-TV for 'Weekend.'
  - Dedicated photograph, 1980; MS137.002.009.00002 (Box 9)
    The photograph shows two men, each having dedicated the photograph to Reuven.
  - Distinguished achievement in journalism award by the University of Southern California School of Journalism and its Alumni Association, 1982; MS137.002.009.00003 (Box 9)
    Drawing and plaque in one frame.
- Audiovisual materials, 1974 -- 2008; MS137.003; 2.4 Linear Feet; 1 Digital Object(s); 1 Gigabytes
  This series contains VHS tapes, Beta tapes, and one DVD, mostly of NBC documentaries and special reports. There are also specific Reuven Frank documentaries, including The Tunnel. Dates range from 1973-2008. There are 31 VHS tapes, 9 Beta Tapes, and 1 DVD.
  This series is arranged alphabetically by title.
  - 50th Anniversary: Huntley-Brinkley Report, 2008; MS137.003.005.00001 (Case 5)
    DVD; Frank, Reuven
  - America Works When America Works, NBC, 1981; MS137.003.005.00002 (Case 5)
    videocassette; Frank, Reuven
  - Ames, 1980; MS137.003.005.00003 (Case 5)
  - If It's A Gnome It Must be Zurich, 1999; MS137.003.005.00004 (Case 5)
  - If Japan Can Why Can't We, 11/2 hrs, 1980; MS137.003.005.00005 (Case 5)
  - If Japan Can...Why Can't We, 90:00 Minutes, 1980; MS137.003.005.00006 (Case 5)
  - Judge Judy EP.026 30;00, Divine Brown, 1990; MS137.003.005.00007 (Case 5)
  - Media Almanac A World Affairs Television Production, 1990; MS137.003.005.00008 (Case 5)
  - NBC Special Report: "The Tunnel," Air Date: 12/10/62, 1990; MS137.003.005.00009 (Case 5)
  - Network News in the Age of Cable, 1997-10-25; MS137.003.005.00010 (Case 5)
  - Nuclear Power in France, 1988-03-12; MS137.003.005.00011 (Case 5)
  - Nuclear Power Doc. In France It Works, 1987-04-03; MS137.003.005.00012 (Case 5)
  - Nuke Power Doc, 1987-03-11; MS137.003.005.00013 (Case 5)
    Betacam (TM); Frank, Reuven
  - Panama Canal-Dub, 1997-01; MS137.003.005.00014 (Case 5)
  - Pensions "The Biggest Lump of Money in the World", 1985-08-07; MS137.003.005.00015 (Case 5)
  - Quality...or Else Part One: The Global Marketplace, 1991-10-03; MS137.003.005.00016 (Case 5)
  - Quality...Or Else Part Two: Change To Survive, 10/3/91, 1991; MS137.003.005.00017 (Case 5)
  - CC-M "Quality...Or Else" part 3 in Progress, 1991-09-18; MS137.003.005.00018 (Case 5)
  - Quality...Or Else Part Three: How to Hit the Moving Target, 1991-10-03; MS137.003.005.00019 (Case 5)
  - Reuven Frank Booknotes, 1991-08-08; MS137.003.005.00020 (Case 5)
  - Road to Spandau, 1992; MS137.003.005.00021 (Case 5)
  - I Witness Video S-Bahn Stops At Freedom, 1980; MS137.003.005.00022 (Case 5)
  - The Biggest Lump of Money In the World, 90 mins, 1985-08-07; MS137.003.005.00023 (Case 5)
  - World Affairs The Editors-Nazi War Criminals in Canada Part I and II, 1980; MS137.003.005.00024 (Case 5)
  - The Japan They Don't Talk About, 1986-04-28; MS137.003.005.00025 (Case 5)
  - The Japan They Don't Talk About-(DUBB), 1988-03-14; MS137.003.005.00026 (Case 5)
  - The Japan They Don't Talk About-(DUBB), 1988-03-14; MS137.003.005.00027 (Case 5)
  - NBC The Pension Cookie Jar DUB, 1998; MS137.003.005.00028 (Case 5)
  - NBC The Pension Cookie Jar DUB Betamax, 1998; MS137.003.005.00029 (Case 5)
  - NBC The Pension Cookie Jar DUB, 1998; MS137.003.005.00030 (Case 5)
  - NBC The Pension Cookie Jar DUB, 1998; MS137.003.005.00031 (Case 5)
  - The Road to Spandau, 1982-08-04; MS137.003.006.00001 (Case 6)
  - The Tunnel Pts 1 of 2 Film Xfer, Part 1 of 2, 1988-03-16; MS137.003.006.00002 (Case 6)
  - The Tunnel Pts 1 of 2 Film Xfer, Part 2 of 2, 1988-03-16; MS137.003.006.00003 (Case 6)
  - NBC The Tunnel Part 1 of 2 Dub, 1980; MS137.003.006.00004 (Case 6)
  - Tunnel Emmy Awards, 1980; MS137.003.006.00005 (Case 6)
  - Weekend/Reuven Frank Reel #1, 1974 -- 1978; MS137.003.006.00006 (Case 6)
  - Weekend/Reuven Frank Reel #2, 1975 -- 1976; MS137.003.006.00007 (Case 6)
  - Weekend Reuven Frank Reel #3, 1976 -- 1979; MS137.003.006.00008 (Case 6)
  - When America Works, 1985-08-07; MS137.003.006.00009 (Case 6)
  - Zurich, 1979; MS137.003.006.00010 (Case 6)
  - The Huntley-Brinkley Report and Remembering Reuven Frank, MS137.003.00001
    Video celebrating the life of Reuven Frank and his work on The Huntley-Brinkley Report put on by NBC news and hosted by Tom Brokaw.
- Additional accessions, 1940 -- 2005; MS137.004; 3.6 Linear Feet; 1 Digital Object(s)
  - Inscribed books and awards, 1960 -- 2000; MS137-001 (Box 1)
    Former barcode 39090015520717g
  - The New Leader and other publications; awards; and photos, 1940 -- 2005; MS137-002 (Box 2)
  - Trade publications and awards, 1980 -- 2000; MS137-003 (Box 3)
    former barcode 39090015520741g